<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Posts on Cave Diving Spain</title><link>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/post/</link><description>Recent content in Posts on Cave Diving Spain</description><generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 21:16:59 +0100</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://buceo.avances123.es/en/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Topography of the first 200m of Cueva del Agua</title><link>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/topography-of-the-first-200m-of-cueva-del-agua/</link><pubDate>Fri, 08 Dec 2023 21:16:59 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/topography-of-the-first-200m-of-cueva-del-agua/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/mapa_poly.png" alt="Featured image of post Topography of the first 200m of Cueva del Agua" />&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>In my previous writings, I&amp;rsquo;ve mentioned my habit of mapping the galleries when I visit Cueva del Agua in Murcia. My goal is to explore increasingly challenging areas to continue improving the process. In my last expedition, my intention was to delve into the 600-meter labyrinth, known for being the section with the highest number of topographic pools throughout the cave&amp;rsquo;s extent, just before the 850-meter stretch. However, I encountered an issue: my vehicle, the scooter, is quite old and has problems with water ingress. Therefore, my focus shifted, and I decided to thoroughly traverse all the installed lines in the cave, carrying out the topography process. Unfortunately, due to percolation and the conditions created by my own presence, turbid water hindered my vision, preventing me from clearly seeing the template used for mapping.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/salto.png"
width="1000"
height="443"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/salto_hu5443163147804593312.png 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/salto_hu12367870716374871380.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="One of the jumps at 100m"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="225"
data-flex-basis="541px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-topography">The topography&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The original topography has a black background to enhance the cave&amp;rsquo;s natural colors. Additionally, I&amp;rsquo;ve created an &lt;a class="link" href="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/mapa_poly_negativo.png" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>alternative version&lt;/a> with a white background and complementary colors to facilitate printing.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/mapa_poly.png"
width="3812"
height="4686"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/mapa_poly_hu16268905434690309345.png 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/mapa_poly_hu17386728237991615338.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Topography of the first 200m of Cueva del Agua"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="81"
data-flex-basis="195px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="key-features-of-the-map">Key Features of the Map&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>I proceeded to cartographically trace the cave&amp;rsquo;s route in its state at the time of the topography&amp;rsquo;s publication, indicating the corresponding date. In the map, each segment of this route is represented by a color code reflecting the tonality present in the cave. The main line, marked in orange and meticulously established by the exploration group, has been drawn with a thicker stroke, while the secondary lines are represented with thinner strokes in white or yellow, depending on their chromatic correspondence in the cave. The non-installed segments, identified as jumps, are outlined with finer strokes and in blue to highlight their nature as potential routes that are not physically present but are useful for planning cave itineraries and calculating necessary equipment such as spools and cookies.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The map also features reference marks every 100 meters and 200 meters, visible to the diver underwater, represented by a directional arrow. Additionally, a schematic point indicating the entrance, represented not by the pool but by the first characteristic rock formation in the shape of a Y, is included, found at an approximate depth of 6 to 7 meters upon entering the cave.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The segments outlined in thin blue strokes, as mentioned earlier, correspond to topographic sections of my own exploration that have been uninstalled and serve only as jump indicators on the line.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The topography has been carried out with an error precision of 0.1 meters in both length and depth and a margin of 5 degrees in the heading of measurements; the length of &amp;ldquo;jump&amp;rdquo; type lines is not included in the statistics.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="project-explanation">Project Explanation&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The project&amp;rsquo;s purpose lies in creating a topography specifically adapted for underwater navigation, focusing on divers and excluding details irrelevant to this practice. This model will solely and exclusively focus on the representation of the polygonal layout. While this might lack significance in terrestrial cave topography, it is crucial for diving, serving as a cardinal guide within the cave environment and physically perceivable by divers.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2.png"
width="1000"
height="443"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2_hu4430889091909901013.png 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2_hu15569489273028123134.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="One of the jumps at 100m"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="225"
data-flex-basis="541px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>To date, the main polygonal line and its secondary branches have been delineated up to a depth of 200 meters. However, there are areas pending cartography, such as the farthest region from the Chara galleries and the closure of the sea circuit. Despite the exploration beyond these sections, the precision of the measurements made has not been optimal (with a margin of error in the order of decimeters). These less accurate measurements will not be disclosed until reaching the same level of precision as the rest, considering that the inherent complexities in wall measurements and the consistency of depth measurements are less relevant to the diving community.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The project&amp;rsquo;s development will continue with the same methodology but at a faster pace, thanks to the complete automation of the tracing up to the 850 reference point. Presenting this section at present is believed to be highly useful for students, instructors, and tourists making their initial immersion in the area, providing them with a clear vision of the path to follow within the cave without delving into details about walls or depths, aspects that, due to their complexity or constancy, are less essential for divers.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="current-topography">Current Topography&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In the current topography field, an abundance of historical information such as drawings, photos, and old lines can create confusion for present-day divers. Therefore, the focus is on mapping only the lines installed as of the current date, providing a clear and precise representation. This approach will allow divers to have updated information for safer and more efficient navigation, maintaining the integrity of historical data for reference and analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/topo_actual.png"
width="941"
height="701"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/topo_actual_hu11466960697709014635.png 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/topo_actual_hu7909580410633463076.png 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Current Topography"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="134"
data-flex-basis="322px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="data-integrity-and-peer-review">Data Integrity and Peer Review&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>The collected data has been processed using specialized software in topography, minimizing the complexity associated with loop closures and the systematic storage of acquired information. Furthermore, an open review mechanism has been enabled to encourage transparency and correction of potential errors. This approach has been implemented through a collaborative platform &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/avances123/topografias/blob/master/cda/las_T/cova.th" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>(Online Data)&lt;/a>, where any individual has the opportunity to cross-verify the data and, if necessary, suggest corrections through a &amp;lsquo;pull request.&amp;rsquo; Since this data is available in an open-source format, it facilitates access and utilization by anyone interested in the field.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/IMG_20231202_182833.jpg"
width="732"
height="976"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/IMG_20231202_182833_hu17128730876669826165.jpg 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/IMG_20231202_182833_hu9358066124243530595.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Data on the template"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="75"
data-flex-basis="180px"
>
&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/cave_m.jpg"
width="1207"
height="1645"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/cave_m_hu15129270513788843530.jpg 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/cave_m_hu15845062555048954813.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Polygonal before decorating"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="73"
data-flex-basis="176px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="global-statistics-of-the-entire-cave">Global Statistics of the Entire Cave&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This presentation offers a comprehensive statistical summary of the thread segment corresponding to Cueva del Agua up to a depth of 200 meters. Each data row encompasses a relevant topographic survey, usually associated with a gallery or relevant segment. It is worth noting that stations and segments classified as jumps are not considered in this statistic, reflected in multiple rows containing pure measurements of the cave&amp;rsquo;s dimensions, excluding such elements from analysis.&lt;/p>
&lt;div class="codeblock">
&lt;header>
&lt;span class="codeblock-lang">&lt;/span>
&lt;button
class="codeblock-copy"
data-id="codeblock-id-0"
data-copied-text="Copied!"
>
Copy
&lt;/button>
&lt;/header>
&lt;code id="codeblock-id-0" style="display:none;">Title Length Depth Explored Approx. Duplicate Surface Shots Stations
Cueva_del_Agua 833 13 0 264 0 0 131 157
Las_Gemelas 164 11 0 0 0 0 21 27
gemelas1 68 8 0 0 0 0 9 10
gemelas2 13 4 0 0 0 0 1 2
gemelas3 31 6 0 0 0 0 3 4
galeria_soto 5 1 0 0 0 0 2 3
galeria_verde 17 5 0 0 0 0 4 5
union_gemelas 30 4 0 0 0 0 2 3
De_0_a_100 109 4 0 0 0 0 19 22
primeros_metros 46 2 0 0 0 0 7 8
stress 27 4 0 0 0 0 6 7
encajonada 37 1 0 0 0 0 6 7
Caverna 128 11 0 10 0 0 41 50
hilo_caverna 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 7 8
caverna_gemelas 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 2 3
buclecito 30 3 0 0 0 0 9 10
caverna_mar 10 0 0 10 0 0 5 6
moto 37 8 0 0 0 0 6 7
a_gemelas2 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 3 4
restricciones_cartel 52 4 0 0 0 0 9 12
restriccion1 26 2 0 0 0 0 5 6
restriccion2 18 2 0 0 0 0 3 4
restriccion3 8 0 0 0 0 0 1 2
De_100_a_200 431 5 0 254 0 0 50 58
bucle 177 5 0 0 0 0 20 21
la_cruz 63 1 0 63 0 0 10 12
eje1 36 1 0 36 0 0 6 7
eje2 27 0 0 27 0 0 4 5
zig_zag1 76 0 0 76 0 0 7 8
ventana_larga 31 0 0 31 0 0 5 6
ventana_corta 17 0 0 17 0 0 3 4
chara1 22 0 0 22 0 0 2 3
chara2 45 0 0 45 0 0 3 4&lt;/code>&lt;pre>&lt;code class="">Title Length Depth Explored Approx. Duplicate Surface Shots Stations
Cueva_del_Agua 833 13 0 264 0 0 131 157
Las_Gemelas 164 11 0 0 0 0 21 27
gemelas1 68 8 0 0 0 0 9 10
gemelas2 13 4 0 0 0 0 1 2
gemelas3 31 6 0 0 0 0 3 4
galeria_soto 5 1 0 0 0 0 2 3
galeria_verde 17 5 0 0 0 0 4 5
union_gemelas 30 4 0 0 0 0 2 3
De_0_a_100 109 4 0 0 0 0 19 22
primeros_metros 46 2 0 0 0 0 7 8
stress 27 4 0 0 0 0 6 7
encajonada 37 1 0 0 0 0 6 7
Caverna 128 11 0 10 0 0 41 50
hilo_caverna 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 7 8
caverna_gemelas 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 2 3
buclecito 30 3 0 0 0 0 9 10
caverna_mar 10 0 0 10 0 0 5 6
moto 37 8 0 0 0 0 6 7
a_gemelas2 0 0.000000 0 0 0 0 3 4
restricciones_cartel 52 4 0 0 0 0 9 12
restriccion1 26 2 0 0 0 0 5 6
restriccion2 18 2 0 0 0 0 3 4
restriccion3 8 0 0 0 0 0 1 2
De_100_a_200 431 5 0 254 0 0 50 58
bucle 177 5 0 0 0 0 20 21
la_cruz 63 1 0 63 0 0 10 12
eje1 36 1 0 36 0 0 6 7
eje2 27 0 0 27 0 0 4 5
zig_zag1 76 0 0 76 0 0 7 8
ventana_larga 31 0 0 31 0 0 5 6
ventana_corta 17 0 0 17 0 0 3 4
chara1 22 0 0 22 0 0 2 3
chara2 45 0 0 45 0 0 3 4&lt;/code>&lt;/pre>&lt;/div>
&lt;h2 id="future-improvements">Future Improvements&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>The aim is to maintain the design&amp;rsquo;s simplicity, but the inclusion of symbols to represent restrictions, shafts, or chimneys of great importance on the map is under consideration.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>A section dedicated exclusively to relevant articles will be established to ensure the permanent availability of the most updated and comprehensive topography.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, georeferencing on the surface orthophoto will be carried out, and a three-dimensional model will be generated to offer a more complete and precise spatial representation.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2t.jpg"
width="2704"
height="1520"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2t_hu6366018928612686805.jpg 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/topografia-de-los-primeros-200m-de-cueva-del-agua/2t_hu10745911241355577147.jpg 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Second T in Cueva del Agua"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="177"
data-flex-basis="426px"
>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Another application for Blender</title><link>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/another-application-for-blender/</link><pubDate>Sat, 07 Jan 2023 16:28:39 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/another-application-for-blender/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/otra-aplicacion-para-blender/banner.png" alt="Featured image of post Another application for Blender" />&lt;h1 id="motivation">Motivation&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I bought a second-hand compressor, quite old but very cheap, and now I&amp;rsquo;m already filling tanks with it very satisfactorily. I&amp;rsquo;m very happy even though it&amp;rsquo;s something I should have done a long time ago; I was tired of having to plan where and when to fill bottles and spending gasoline to get there. Besides, I&amp;rsquo;m overcoming the fear of handling the compressor and the bottles. I used to feel apprehensive about the high pressure involved, but as always happens, after about twenty fills, the body gets used to the valve&amp;rsquo;s blowing of overpressure and purging.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>The compressor runs on gasoline, and I use it to fill air, but sometimes I refill bottles that previously had nitrox, and I&amp;rsquo;d like to know in advance the resulting mixture. For this, there are many blending apps for all systems, but by programming it from scratch, I can revisit the notes from the Blender course and also continue gaining proficiency in creating GUI in Python.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="ideas-and-development">Ideas and Development&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;m going to create a program that takes the mixture with which the bottle is provided and the mixture you desire for the bottle. The system will then return the bars of O2, He, and air that you need to apply to achieve it, which is typical in this kind of applications.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, it has another option that I&amp;rsquo;ll likely use the most, which is to tell you the resulting mixture when filling any bottle with air. Also, I&amp;rsquo;ll include the prices of the gases sold in Spain, including the price of compressed air, which always has a fixed cost in the industry. I don&amp;rsquo;t understand why, so if someone comes by someday and I want to charge them for the fill, I&amp;rsquo;ll charge them a fair amount, never more or less.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="where-to-find-it">Where to Find It&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ve uploaded it to a &lt;a class="link" href="https://github.com/avances123/gasblender" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>GitHub project&lt;/a>. It&amp;rsquo;s a Python script, and in the same repository, there&amp;rsquo;s a file with the dependencies it needs to run.&lt;/p>
&lt;h1 id="future">Future&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>I hope to implement a small database to keep track of my fills and thus monitor the maintenance needed for the compressor. This change might even lead to transitioning directly from Python to a web-based application.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Meteorology for Diving</title><link>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/meteorology-for-diving/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Apr 2022 00:47:56 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/meteorology-for-diving/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/entrada.png.webp" alt="Featured image of post Meteorology for Diving" />&lt;h1 id="how-to-determine-weather-for-diving">How to Determine Weather for Diving&lt;/h1>
&lt;h2 id="introduction">Introduction&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>Whenever planning a dive, one of our primary concerns is the condition of the sea at the time of immersion. Our favorite hobby takes place outdoors and &lt;strong>within&lt;/strong> the marine environment, making us heavily reliant on meteorology to successfully conduct our dives.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In my opinion, extensively planning a dive and neglecting a proper interpretation of the expected weather for that day is futile. Weather conditions could necessitate a postponement of the dive, and it&amp;rsquo;s important to ascertain this with the utmost certainty possible.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Certainly, most of us have one way or another to check the sea conditions for our dives. Due to my interest in the subject, I&amp;rsquo;ve always inquired, and in almost all cases, I&amp;rsquo;ve observed the use of mobile weather applications. These apps provide data on waves, wind, etc., are very convenient, free, and always available. However, in this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll focus on other, slightly more hidden yet equally useful sources that can significantly aid us in this task.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>I&amp;rsquo;ll concentrate on data that I haven&amp;rsquo;t seen anyone using, which I can contribute to the diving community. Towards the end of this post, I&amp;rsquo;ll discuss conventional apps and some hidden improvements we can utilize to interpret and make an enhanced forecast.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="meteorological-factors-to-consider">Meteorological Factors to Consider&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To make a proper plan, we should have a computer in front of us and observe various weather factors relevant to diving. Here they are listed, and for all of them, we need to know the geographical point of the dive and the date, as we must check the prediction for that specific place and time.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="significant-wave-height">Significant Wave Height&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>In my opinion, this is the decisive variable determining the feasibility of the dive, requiring the utmost precision in prediction at that point. For this, in the Iberian Peninsula, I use the meteorological model generated by &lt;a class="link" href="https://www.puertos.es/es-es/oceanografia/AccesoSimplificado" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Puertos del Estado&lt;/a>. This model uses wind predictions from AEMET&amp;rsquo;s HARMONIE and HRES-ECMWF for forecasts beyond 48 hours. Additionally, it provides data from observations of several buoys installed near ports, significantly improving the model&amp;rsquo;s accuracy in those areas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For instance, if we want to know about the waves at the Dragonera wreck, located in the port of Tarragona, we could observe the model and its predictive quality at that specific point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/2.png.webp"
width="1615"
height="268"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/2.png_hu8708285690629023918.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/2.png_hu355433170010402531.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Recent prediction/observation days in Tarragona"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="602"
data-flex-basis="1446px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Luckily for the Dragonera wreck, we have observations from a buoy recording hourly granularity of wave height. There are several other points, always buoys aiding wave prediction &lt;em>in the ports&lt;/em>, as we are more concerned about waves in port areas than in diving areas.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/1.png.webp"
width="838"
height="635"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/1.png_hu18157865649175420721.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/1.png_hu16084508332393472140.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Buoys with updated wave height data"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="131"
data-flex-basis="316px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This doesn&amp;rsquo;t mean we have to manually interpolate the prediction at the desired point; the model itself provides a prediction across its grid points. Thus, we can check the prediction for our point.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/3.png.webp"
width="1019"
height="687"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/3.png_hu18153683925739452024.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/3.png_hu16913286952487153790.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Wave prediction points"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="148"
data-flex-basis="355px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>When we check a point, we can see the data in a table format for all variables in the model, not just significant height. We can also view wave period and direction, the component of swell or wind that affects the wave, etc. Additionally, there are wind data at that point, which could be useful for understanding local winds and the sea state through another experienced observer&amp;rsquo;s perspective.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/4.png.webp"
width="1050"
height="475"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/4.png_hu2710413128485115386.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/4.png_hu5596130804796961678.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Prediction at a point"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="221"
data-flex-basis="530px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Moreover, &lt;a class="link" href="https://myocean.marine.copernicus.eu/data?view=dataset&amp;amp;dataset=MEDSEA_ANALYSISFORECAST_WAV_006_017" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Copernicus&lt;/a> provides this WAN model without being improved by AEMET&amp;rsquo;s HARMONIE.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="water-temperature">Water Temperature&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This variable significantly affects diving, but it&amp;rsquo;s not predicted as such since it&amp;rsquo;s quite easy to deduce the temperature based on the time of year and past observations for that date.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a class="link" href="https://myocean.marine.copernicus.eu/light" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Copernicus&lt;/a>, we can check the temperature prediction at our ocean point and access a history of the analyzed model.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/5.png.webp"
width="1913"
height="928"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/5.png_hu15463153307385759750.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/5.png_hu8041965586688895485.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Daily sea temperature prediction"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="206"
data-flex-basis="494px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Here, I&amp;rsquo;d like to offer another source quite useful for diving trips, where we want to know the temperature at a point on the planet beyond our experience and latitudes. &lt;a class="link" href="https://climexp.knmi.nl/monthly_overview_world_weather/index.cgi?var=sst_ncep_w&amp;amp;mon1=jan&amp;amp;year1=2021&amp;amp;anomalie=nee&amp;amp;kort=nee&amp;amp;expert=nee&amp;amp;type=kaartwereld" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>WMO&lt;/a> allows us to explore the average temperature of a month at any point on the planet. It might not be precise, but it can assist in planning a trip, considering the date and destination.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/6.png.webp"
width="876"
height="870"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/6.png_hu583121573678615602.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/6.png_hu8775532450049670691.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Monthly water temperature information"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="100"
data-flex-basis="241px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Additionally, NASA has a mission called &lt;a class="link" href="https://podaac.jpl.nasa.gov/dataset/MUR-JPL-L4-GLOB-v4.1" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>MUR&lt;/a> that measures global sea temperature, viewable using NASA&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a class="link" href="https://soto.podaac.earthdatacloud.nasa.gov/?v=-18.78720059082591,30.727507641081075,21.28282587652165,50.51208320933394" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>worldview&lt;/a> tool.&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="current">Current&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>This variable also affects diving. What diver hasn&amp;rsquo;t dreamt of knowing the days without a current at that incredible wreck? However, I&amp;rsquo;ve studied this variable less up to now. I see a data point for water speed in the horizontal plane, but I haven&amp;rsquo;t yet comprehended which vertical levels are used for measurement and/or prediction.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>In &lt;a class="link" href="https://myocean.marine.copernicus.eu/data?view=dataset&amp;amp;dataset=MEDSEA_ANALYSISFORECAST_PHY_006_013" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Copernicus&lt;/a>, we can view current data in various datasets, and this variable is available on Windy too. I haven&amp;rsquo;t had the chance to repeat dives enough to verify its usefulness personally, but it would be great to do so.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/7.png.webp"
width="1709"
height="896"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/7.png_hu15542851076304504112.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/7.png_hu3876910916910007943.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="Marine current prediction"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="190"
data-flex-basis="457px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;h3 id="rain-and-wind">Rain and Wind&lt;/h3>
&lt;p>While it&amp;rsquo;s advisable to check these variables, I consider them less critical, although they could lead to others like &lt;strong>visibility&lt;/strong> that are of interest to us. By studying past days of rain and storms, we can deduce good or bad visibility, for instance.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>We can also plan for scenarios like sailing, or if carrying dive equipment requires us to be out in the rain, or any other more eccentric reasons these variables might affect us. In any case, for these, I refer to the next section on conventional apps.&lt;/p>
&lt;h2 id="the-conventional-route">The Conventional Route&lt;/h2>
&lt;p>To check the weather at a point, we&amp;rsquo;ll use the application &lt;a class="link" href="https://windy.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener"
>Windy&lt;/a>, among others available, but this app is becoming quite popular among users due to its variety of layers, models, and data.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>For a serious plan, I recommend using a PC instead of a mobile device if possible. There, we can make use of the entire application interface. We can view information on all previously described variables, sacrificing a bit of precision at the point but gaining the ability to predict in any part of the planet, not just the Iberian Peninsula.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Apart from checking waves here, we can also explore &amp;ldquo;what the day will be like&amp;rdquo; in general (temperature, rain, and wind). Instead of simply opening the app and checking the initial prediction it provides, I recommend a &lt;strong>multimodel view&lt;/strong> of these variables. Here&amp;rsquo;s how:&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/8.png.webp"
width="1915"
height="249"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/8.png_hu10349930242904171665.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/8.png_hu4772426397246665515.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="1. Go to the point prediction and click the compare button"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="769"
data-flex-basis="1845px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/9.png.webp"
width="1438"
height="819"
srcset="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/9.png_hu13332880161087571456.webp 480w, https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/meteorologia-para-el-buceo/9.png_hu2750586246982387981.webp 1024w"
loading="lazy"
alt="2. View the same data produced by several models"
class="gallery-image"
data-flex-grow="175"
data-flex-basis="421px"
>&lt;/p>
&lt;p>This will help us determine consensus or discrepancies among models. It&amp;rsquo;s essentially the same weather check, but seen through 4 or 5 sources, providing a broader perspective on the uncertainty levels the models hold for that specific point in time.&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Welcome</title><link>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/welcome/</link><pubDate>Fri, 10 Dec 2021 23:30:26 +0100</pubDate><guid>https://buceo.avances123.es/en/p/welcome/</guid><description>&lt;img src="https://buceo.avances123.es/es/p/bienvenida/bienvenida.jpg" alt="Featured image of post Welcome" />&lt;h1 id="explanation-about-my-scuba-diving-blog">Explanation about my scuba diving blog&lt;/h1>
&lt;p>Hello everyone! My name is Fabio Rueda, and I&amp;rsquo;m a certified cave diver by the IANTD agency. For over 5 years, I&amp;rsquo;ve been exploring and diving in underwater caves worldwide, and I love sharing my experience and knowledge with other diving enthusiasts.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>Cave diving is an activity that requires high technical skill and a profound understanding of water safety. That&amp;rsquo;s why I&amp;rsquo;ve obtained several additional certifications to conduct this type of diving safely.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>During my cave dives, I always ensure to follow the best safety practices and respect the environment. I also take responsibility for regularly maintaining and checking my diving equipment to ensure its proper functioning.&lt;/p>
&lt;p>If you&amp;rsquo;re interested in exploring the underwater world through cave diving, feel free to get in touch with me. I&amp;rsquo;m ready to help you enjoy this exciting activity safely and share my knowledge with you. I hope to dive with you soon!&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>